<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Short vindication of Phil. Scot's Defence of the Scots abdicating Darien being in answer to the challenge of the author of the defence of that settlement, to prove the Spanish title to Darien, by inheritance, marriage, donation, purchase, reversion, surrender, or conquest : with a prefatory reply, to the false and scurrillous aspersions of the new author of the Just and modest vindication, &amp;c., and some animadversions on the material part of it, relating to the title of Darien.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2299A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12300</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13016579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13016579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96557</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96557)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:31 or 1689:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Short vindication of Phil. Scot's Defence of the Scots abdicating Darien being in answer to the challenge of the author of the defence of that settlement, to prove the Spanish title to Darien, by inheritance, marriage, donation, purchase, reversion, surrender, or conquest : with a prefatory reply, to the false and scurrillous aspersions of the new author of the Just and modest vindication, &amp;c., and some animadversions on the material part of it, relating to the title of Darien.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Walter, 17th/18th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"This book is a further effort of Walter Herries [or Harris] and is included in the ban of Parliament" [of Scotland]--J. Scott, Bibl. of ... the Darien Company, 1904, p. 29.</note>
                  <note>"Defence of the Scots abdicating Darien" has been variously attributed to James Hodges, Walter Harris, and Archibald Foyer.</note>
                  <note>On question of Ferguson's authorship, see DNB.</note>
                  <note>This item can be found at reels 741:31 and 1689:35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hodges, James.</term>
               <term>Harris, Walter, 17th/18th cent.</term>
               <term>Foyer, Archibald.</term>
               <term>Ferguson, Robert, d. 1714. --  Just and modest vindication of the Scots design, for the having established a colony at Darien.</term>
               <term>Defence of the Scots abdicating Darien.</term>
               <term>Darien Scots' Colony, 1698-1700.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Commercial policy.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1689-1745.</term>
               <term>Panama --  Colonization.</term>
               <term>Panama --  Discovery and exploration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96557:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT VINDICATION OF <hi>Phil. Scot</hi>'s Defence OF THE <hi>Scots</hi> Abdicating <hi>DARIEN:</hi> BEING In Anſwer to the Challenge of the Author of the Defence of that Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to prove the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Title to <hi>Darien,</hi> by Inheritance, Marriage, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Purchaſe, Reverſion, Surrender, or Conqueſt. WITH A Prefatory Reply, to the Falſe and Scurrillous Aſperſions, of the New Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of, <hi>The Juſt and Modeſt Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. And ſome Animadverſions on the material Part of it, relating to the Title of <hi>DARIEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Non qui multa ſed qui multum dicit bene dicit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:96557:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96557:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE moſt genuine and beſt meant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Man, being lyable not only to Miſconſtruction, but Reproach, 'tis the leſs ſurpriſing to meet with either of theſe in the preſent Caſe, conſidering the ſmall Proportion I bear to a numerous Party, who are ſo far dipt in a Project, that notwithſtanding a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them by this Time begin to perceive the Errour they have been led unto, yet they will not diſintangle themſelves; and if any Perſon ſhould take upon him to unblind, them he must expect to have his Throat cut.</p>
            <p>As my firſt Attempt in this Nature is not only cenſur'd Bold, but Impudent, by the Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the <hi>Caledonian</hi> Project, ſo it has been attended with Menaces enough, that I ſhould not eat my <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Dinner. The friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Advices I have received of my ſudden Fate don't in the leaſt make my Pen ſtagger from Vindicating what I have already offer'd to ſhow the Impracticability of that Project, for which altho' I am at preſent baſely cenſur'd, by a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and headſtrong Party, yet, I doubt not of receiving the Approbation of the moderate and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96557:3"/>judicious Part of that Nation before the Jubilee be over, my Theme being both just, and well deſign'd to the Proprietors of that Stock.</p>
            <p>I could have wiſh'd that this gentle Author, who Effects ſo much Modeſty, Senſe, and good Manners, had ſtood by his Text, and had taken more convincing Ways of confuting what I have written on the <hi>Darien</hi> Subject: For, however neceſſary h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinks it for his Argument to treat it and me with Reproach, yet he will gain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by but few Proſelytes to his Opinion: And if he had employ'd his Mathematical Head in diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what I have offer'd in Defence of the Abdication, with ſome of thoſe <hi>Euclid</hi> Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, wherewith he would let us know that he abounds, his ſlanderous and perſonal Reflections might be the better credited: But as he has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd nothing, either to juſtifie the Conduct of the Directors of that Company, or to diſprove one Syllable of what's offer'd against the <hi>Darien</hi> Project, except the Inſtance of Mr. <hi>Wafer,</hi> which he would have the World take for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a Lye, and make uſe of that to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow my Faith; I hope that (if the whole Diſcourſe does not carry Demonſtration enough along with it) it may ſtand firm till ſuch Time as it is repeal'd by Dint of Argument: And as for this Paſſage velating to Mr. <hi>Wafer,</hi> I ſhall juſtifie it before I proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96557:3"/>
            <p>In the first Place, I deſire that it may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as a Preliminary, that if. Mr. <hi>Wafer</hi> had met with ſo egregious a Romance, and ſo near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relating to him publickly in Print, he ought in Juſtice, both to the Company and himſelf, to have inſtantly detected it's Falſhoods. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' he lives very near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> and had the Peruſal of the ſame Book the first Day it was publiſhed (which is above Two Months ago) yet he hath been ſo far from offering to diſprove it, that he hath ſince expreſt himſelf to Perſons of unqueſtionable Credit, that if he had known of my Intention, or had not thereby been anticipated from Publiſhing his own Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, he would have ſaid a great Deal more on that Subject.</p>
            <p>I must needs own, that he was ignorant of my Deſign of Publiſhing that, or any Thing elſe; but I must tell you, that about the ſame Time, he thought to have oblig'd the Company to recompenſe him for his Diſappointment, or to have expos'd them to the Publick: And to confirm what I herein aſſert, 'tis very well known to a great many in Town, that about Four Months agoe, he preſented a Memorial to a certain <hi>Scots</hi> Perſon of Quality, containing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Syllable of what I have wrote, as likewiſe ſome more which I deſign'dly left out, becauſe it particulariz'd ſome Perſons whom I had no Inclination to mention.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96557:4"/>
            <p>He was kept in Hopes of ſome Gratification, and I believe he might have been eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with, but what I have wrote from his own Mouth and Memorial, I am ſo far from diſtruſting he will retract, or can be brib'd to deny, that I firmly believe he gave no Occaſion to this Author, to make uſe of his Name to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thus upon the World: And to confirm me the more in this Belief, it is not above Three Days ſince he came to my Lodging to acquaint me, that a Book was newly publiſh'd in Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the <hi>Darien</hi> Settlement, but he had not ſeen it; on which I ask'd, If any Perſons had been with him from the Company, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to paſs from what he had ſaid and wrote? to which he anſwer'd, <hi>No.</hi> I ſhow'd him the Book and Paſſage in it, relating to him, which having perus'd, he told me, That he was ſo far from paſſing from it, that he wonder'd how that Author ſhould be ſo confident, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on what he ſhould anſwer.</p>
            <p>If this is not enough to juſtifie that Paſſage relating to <hi>Wafer,</hi> by which our Author ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the Truth of the Whole to be try'd, I ſhall prove it, <hi>Viva voce,</hi> if need be; and ſhall ſay no more to it here, but only ſhow you the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion which our Author makes uſe of in the <hi>18</hi> th Page of his Preface, to clear his Party of that Imputation, To wit; <hi>Nor can any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Renouncing of common Senſë, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Gentlemen employ'd by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96557:4"/>Company to confer and tranſact with Mr.</hi> Wafer, <hi>could be guilty of ſuch Weakneſs and Folly, as to reveal and detect to him their Deſign upon</hi> Darien, <hi>in that the whole Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that Undertaking depended entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon it's being kept and preſerv'd a Secret.</hi> If our learned Author would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to brutal Ignorance, to differ in any Point from his Conception of Things, I might be allow'd to detect the Weakneſs or Innocence of this ſtrong Argument; and would ask him, if at the Conference between the ſame Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Mr. <hi>Wafer,</hi> at <hi>Pontaks</hi>'s, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject was not <hi>Darien?</hi> I would likewiſe know whether the Collection of Guineas for him at that Meeting was not to keep him from Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of himſelf till they acquainted the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with his Qualifications to ſerve them? As alſo, whether that Article in the Contract, whereby he receiv'd <hi>20</hi> Guineas, was not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Stopping the Publiſhing of this Book for the Space of a Month, till the Company and he ſhould come to Terms for Suppreſſing it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together? 'Tis evident enough, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that Book or Journal relates to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Darien;</hi> as likewiſe, that <hi>Wafer</hi>'s Talent as to Projects lay no where elſe: Now how far this Mathematical Argument of our Author will demonſtrate <hi>Wafer</hi> to be a Fool, and me a Lyar, I ſubmit it to Judgment. In the mean Time, it may be worthy of Remark,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96557:5"/>that this Faction is not calculated for <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> but for a Country where <hi>Wafer</hi> is not to be ſeen and ſpoken with.</p>
            <p>Believing what is already ſaid on this Head to be ſufficient to reinſtate me in my Credit, I ſhall return to the firſt Part of this Preface, where he throws ſome Foul-mouth'd Aſperſions, not only on me, but likewiſe on his Majeſty's Miniſters of State; how corroſpondent that Style is with the Title of his Book, let any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon judge, or if it is not fitter to be bound up with the Volumes of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyterian Eloquence, than left ſingle for the more civil Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts of this Age to peruſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not take upon me to ſay any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to that Miniſter, whom he uſes ſo ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilouſly, believing, that if he thinks it worth his While, he will do himſelf Right; yet I must take upon me to remark, that through the whole Strain of his Calumnies and Invectives, it is not at him alone he points his Thunder, but through the Sides of that State-Officer he wounds and bullies the Rest (be of what Office or Quality they will) who will preſume to act directly or indirectly againſt the <hi>Darien</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and if a Man dares be ſo bold, as to whiſper his Thoughts, either publickly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, in Oppoſition to it, he muſt be mouth'd at, and repreſented as an Enemy to one of His Majeſty's Kingdoms, and is not fit for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he bears; as alſo, that he muſt remember
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96557:5"/>the Fate of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Strafford.</hi> So God ha' Mercy Old <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to that Part of his ſlandrous Story, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he inſinuates, that large Rewards have been beſtow'd on me by that Miniſter; I have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe, that the Perſons, whom he calls Friends, of thoſe State-Councellors, are only feign'd by himſelf, to make the Story paſs the more current: As for my ſelf, I muſt needs own, that when I came from <hi>Scotland,</hi> about Eighteen Years ago, I brought but little Money with me, and what I have purchaſed ſince, has been in Serving the King: But that I either receiv'd or expected any mercinary Reward (as our Author impudently and maliciouſly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates) I muſt tell him, or whoever elſe ſays ſo, that it is a Lye. To reproach me the more, he gives out, that I was expell'd the Navy for Crimes and Miſdemeanours, which is likewiſe falſe, for I was neither expell'd or ever tainted with any baſe or mean Action: The Reaſon of my Leaving that Service, is ſufficiently known to be on the Score of a Rancounter I had at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> with the Commander of the Ship, where I ſerv'd. 'Tis true, the Cloud I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for ſome Months afterwards (being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſtand the Teſt of a Court Martial) induc'd me the eaſier to enter into that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Service, under the Notion of going to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and which I was made ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely to believe for a Twelve-month afterwards;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96557:6"/>but by what has happen'd it was jumping out of the Frying-pan into the Fire: For after I had ſerv'd them in more Stations than one (with their Approbation) for the Space of <hi>26</hi> Months, and proceeded in their private Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with Five or Six Months Proviſions to a Country where nothing was to be ſeen but Death, Ruine, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mines, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got my Belly full of the Project, obtain'd my Diſcharge with an ample Certificate from the Council of the Collony: And altho' I was Shipwrack'd the very next Day, coming out of their Harbour's Mouth, had my Servant drown'd, eſcaping very narrowly my ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Loſs of what I had; when I came to <hi>England,</hi> I was oblig'd to go to Law with them in <hi>Doctors-Commons</hi> for my Wages, where it coſt me more than I recover'd.</p>
            <p>As for the Meanneſs of my Office and Parts, wherewith our Author upbraids me, I ſhall not offer much on that Head, that ſignifying but little to the Subject in debate; the leſs Force the Weakneſs or Meanneſs of my Argument carries with it, it is the eaſier evinc'd, but as there's nothing appears, but ſlandrons Aſperſions to confute it, it will bear but tittle Weight with the judicious Part of Mankind. The Obſcurity of our Author, indeed, ſhades him from ſuitable Returns to his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; however, I muſt take the Liberty to remark that, notwithſtanding he would make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96557:6"/>us believe he is no <hi>Plagiary;</hi> yet the whole Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of his Diſcourſe is eaſily diſcover'd to be Mr. <hi>F—rs,</hi> almoſt Paragraph by Paragraph, only dreſs'd up with a long-winded Proemium, a Chain of innumerable Tautologies, Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes, and crabbed Abſtruſities, deſignedly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated to Crambo the Reader out of his Senſes; beſides, a few French and Civilian Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Latter of which he might have kept in his Pocket, 'till once the Spaniſh Title to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rien</hi> had been fairly confuted: He has, indeed, left out ſome of the ſowreſt Parts of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Book, which reſlected on his Majeſty, and the Engliſh Government, but he retains ſuch Portions of the ſame Venome, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his affected Mannerlineſs, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, he can't forbear ſpurting it out in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Places, nor from pointing it plainly and diametrically at the Councils, and Government of <hi>England.</hi> The Threats, indeed, are Airy, and ſo the leſs worthy of Regard; yet they may be look'd upon from one who ſits under the Noſe of the ſame Government, to be fraught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with much more Preſumption, than what's offer'd in the Defence of the <hi>Scots</hi> Abdicating <hi>Darien,</hi> to a Company of Merchants.</p>
            <p>But that I may vindicate that Defence from any National Aſperſions, which thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are bigotted to the <hi>Darien</hi> Project, load it with, and who would ſqueeze that ſowre Part from the Managers of the Company, to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96557:7"/>whom it was plainly directed, and apply it to the Body of the Nation; to clear my ſelf of this general Imputation, I muſt refer the Reader to the 6th Page of its <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory,</hi> where I particularly caution it to prevent ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Interpretations. In the next place, I muſt detect the baſe and unfair Methods, which the Author of, <hi>The juſt and modeſt Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> uſeth to wreſt, and pervert what I have ſaid in the Paragraphs, which he cites in his <hi>Preface to the Reader.</hi> The firſt is Page <hi>2.</hi> where he tells you, That I have <hi>aſſum'd the Impudence of aſſerting, that the Motives on which the Proclamations were emitted in the Engliſh</hi> Weſt-India <hi>Plantations, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the Supplying, Relieving, and Aſſiſting the</hi> Scots <hi>at</hi> Darien, <hi>or in any Parts of</hi> America, <hi>where they ſhould ſettle, was becauſe the Government of</hi> England <hi>would not be acceſſary to an Act, which the World might judge to be Felonious.</hi> Now, that the Reader may judge of this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly Gentleman's Integrity, I ſhall rehearſe the Paragraph as I wrote it, where there's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any mention made of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, much leſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment's forbidding, to aſſist or ſupply the <hi>Scots</hi> in any Part of <hi>America,</hi> to wit, <hi>Defence of the</hi> Scots <hi>Abdicating,</hi> Pag. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt. Ded. <hi>If you were thus perſwaded</hi> (directing it to the Managers of the Company) <hi>to run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96557:7"/>on a blind Project, at which the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Part of the World ſtands amaz'd; the</hi> India <hi>Companies of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Holland <hi>laugh at in their Sleeve, and the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind admire, that People in their right Senſes ſhould be guilty of, and if the ſame ſhould miſcarry by your own ill Management (to ſay no worſe on't) 'tis not fair you ſhould ſnarle at your Neighbours, who have no other Hand in your Misfortune, than that they would not be acceſſary to any Act which the World might judge Felonious, and wherein they could not join without engaging themſelves in an unreaſonable War, and in the End to aſſiſt you with Weapons to break their own Heads.</hi> But that I may likewiſe rehearſe the Paragraph, where I had Occaſion to mention the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proclamation or Prohibition. See the Page <hi>156. Laying aſide the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Complaint, and admit the</hi> Scotch <hi>Company to have a Legal Title to their Settlement, was it not reaſonable, that the Goverment of</hi> England <hi>having met with the clandeſtine Declarations, which the</hi> Scotch <hi>Collony had ſpread all over the</hi> Weſt-Indies, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting them over to</hi> Darien, <hi>ſhould take ſuitable Meaſures to prevent the ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of the ſame, and retain their own Subjects: The Declarations are notorious, and muſt be penn'd by ſome Perſon belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96557:8"/>to the Company or Collony, and I preſume the Oppoſite Proclamation or Prohibition was penn'd by ſome</hi> Engliſh <hi>Man, who had ſome Intereſt in the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Plantations.</hi> Now whether our Author uſbers in his juſt and modeſt Vindication, fairly and honeſtly, I ſubmit it to Judgment, or whether I mayn't juſtly retort upon himſelf, again, that ſlanderous Aſperſion relation to <hi>Wafer,</hi> in the <hi>18</hi>th Page of his Preface, <hi>viz. That through the Fellows appearing a Lyar, or uncandid in one Caſe, his Teſtimony ſhould not be receiv'd in any other whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay in the ſame Breath, he backs it with ſuch another Perverſion (altho' not quite ſo malicious) and vents his Choller thus, citing the 7th Page of the Epiſtle Dedicatory, <hi>That I ſhould have taken the Boldneſs to add, in Terms that are moſt ſlanderous, as well as defamatory, that their Attempt of Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the</hi> Iſthmus, <hi>was their Settling a Colony in another Man's Dominions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by Virtue of their Presbyterian Tenet (of Dominions being founded in Grace) the</hi> Scots, <hi>who are the Preſumptive Elect, pretend a Divine Right to the Goods of the Wicked, and ſo take upon them to cloath the Seven Councellors of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, with ſuch another Commiſſion as God gave the</hi> Hebrews, <hi>when they depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of</hi> Egypt. The Injuſtice which this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96557:8"/>Gentleman does me, and the little Servicoe he does his Cauſe, is very apparent; for I don't ſay, that the <hi>Scots</hi> are the Preſumptive Elect (there being no ſuch Word mention'd) nor do I think it. Some Species of Men, indeed, in that Nation are conceited with that Opinion of themſelves, but there are ſeveral Perſons of Worth who will not aſſume that Title; neither do I direct that Dedication to them, but to Directors of the Scots <hi>Affrican</hi> Company, of whom that Sept, who were the Occaſion of the chief Miſmanagement, are of this vain Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. As for <hi>Harris,</hi> whom our Author cites irreverently in the ſame Paragraph, I know him, but <hi>D—l</hi> is ſuch a Stranger to me, that I proteſt, there's none of my Acquaintance I can think of, whoſe Name begins and ends with thoſe Letters: But that muſt be plac'd to the other falſe Notions he. runs on.</p>
            <p>Our Author thinks fit to cite only one Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage more of, <hi>The Defence of the</hi> Scots <hi>Abd.</hi> pag. <hi>16. That juſt as the</hi> Scots <hi>Companies Books were open'd at</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Subſcriptions to their Capital Stock, the Dutch</hi> East <hi>and</hi> West-India <hi>Companies run open-mouth'd to the Lords of</hi> Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>ſhewing what was hatching by the</hi> Scotch <hi>Commiſſioners in their City, to ruine the Trade of the</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces. The Gentleman thinks fit to own this to be true, deſigning to make Two neceſſary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96557:9"/>it; the first is calculated for the Proprietors of the Scots <hi>Affrican</hi> Stock, as the Printing and Reprinting of the Houſe of Commons Addreſs to the King, of the Year <hi>1696,</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> was to inſinuate the Vaſtneſs of the Project, and the Riches that were to be acquir'd by it, when ſuch Foreign People oppos'd it: But that none of thoſe may be deceiv'd by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe he makes of that Paragraph, I must acquaint them in ſhort, that if thoſe <hi>Dutch</hi> Men had known the <hi>Scotch</hi> Companies Project to be on <hi>Darien,</hi> I dare ſay, they would not have taken ſuch Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to oppoſe them. The other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor makes of this is, to ſow ſome malicious Seeds of diſtrust among the People of <hi>England,</hi> and to calumniate His Majeſty and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, as if thoſe were altogether calculated for a <hi>Dutch</hi> Interest. This Mathematical Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, both here and every where elſe, when he has occaſion to diſcharge his Gall on His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and his Government, ſhreuds his Aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under a Religious and Well-meaning Cant, as if they were the Apprehenſions and Deſigns of other People, and not of himſelf.</p>
            <p>This modest Author excuſes himſelf from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying any Thing to the Argument-part of what has been offer'd against the <hi>Darien</hi> Project, it being fully obviated and anticipated by this Book of his, which he ſays was antecedently written on that Subject: How far this is true, let any Man (who will have the Patience, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96557:9"/>puniſh himſelf, to read it) determine. 'Tis pity that it ſhould have lain ſo long in <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio,</hi> and not ſeen the Light, till now moſt People are confirm'd of an adverſe Opinion of the Project, not becauſe it is like to enrich that Company and Nation, but becauſe there's a great Deal of good Money ſquander'd away, which might have been better employ'd. Neither can that Judicious part of Mankind (to whom he recommends his Book) find any more in it of Subſtance than what is already, and leſs barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly expreſs'd in the Original, which this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Parentheſer has only Paraphras'd upon, with a Pedantick Accumulation of Synonimous Words and Repetitions, and has no ways mended it; unleſs he thinks it a ſtrong Way of Arguing, to brawl a Man out of his Reaſon; which, in my Opinion, ſuits better with <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> than the <hi>Aula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed on the Vindication of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the <hi>Scots</hi> Abdicating <hi>Darien,</hi> I must tell you, that the Motives which puſh'd me on to it, were quite different from thoſe of this modeſt Author, or ſome more particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who, beſides the Noiſe themſelves make, may rather encourage than endeavour to cruſh the Clamours of others, it being a Topick war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Precedents, whereby Money has been got, and may ſtill, if it be well manag'd, altho' perhaps, little of it may come to the Share of the Subſcribers.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96557:10"/>
            <p>Any impartial or unprejudic'd Reader, who hath perus'd that Defence, may ſee that it runs in three different Strains; the firſt is in Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the Juſtice of His Majeſty and Councils from the oblique and expreſs Calumnies, in the Defence of the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlemen at <hi>Darien,</hi> which my Duty oblig'd me to as a Subject, and ſo long a Servant of His Majeſty and the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Nation, that what Bread I have eat theſe <hi>18</hi> Years has been theirs, ſave my <hi>Caledonian</hi> Allowance, during that Service, and my Trip to <hi>Darien.</hi> And if in that Part of it, which points at the Errata's of that Author (where he ſets up his Royal Beacons for King <hi>William</hi> to mind, and be aware of) I have offer'd anything inconſiſtent with the Celebrated Hiſtories of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or have not worded it with more Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>Scots</hi> than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians relate it, I leave it to Judgment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Strain of it runs on the Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of the Company, their Miſmanagement of that great Act they are inveſted with, as alſo of the Money of the ſeveral Proprietors where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were intruſted, and of their ſending ſo many worthy Gentlemen, and other brave Fellows on ſo dark an Errand, unprovided of either the Neceſſaries for their Subſiſtance, or Credit to purchaſe any; and of neglecting them in ſo Foreign and deſolate a Country. I have ſaid no more in this than what is notorious, and if I have deviated in any particular, thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96557:10"/>Gentlemen who left the Collony at first, and the reſt who have quitted it ſince, are at liberty to confute me. As for my own Share, I loſt what I had in their Service; when I came home, I was oblig'd to ſue them for what was my due; and when at the Request of ſome Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, I gave a candid Relation of the Collony, their Affairs, and the Improbability of their holding of it; the Managers in <hi>Scotland</hi> not only us'd Means to ſtifle my Credit, but baffl'd and miſrepreſented me here, and when any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe News came at any time, relating to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledonian,</hi> it was cruſh'd and laid on my Back, as the malicious Author of it. I thank God I am the Subject of a Nation, where I breath free Air, and may ſay, that I have been ill us'd by that Company, and am not under the petty Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of ſome Gentlemen, where I must not mutter a Groan, altho' my Oppreſſion were greater, but in a Country where it is no Crime to detect the Errors of as great Societies, and Perſons when they act amiſs.</p>
            <p>The Third and Laſt Strain of that Defence, hints at the Impracticability of the <hi>Darien</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſhowing the little Encouragement the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany has to proſecute a Title to a Colony there, and the ſmall Advantages they can reap by it, either to themſelves or Nation, tho' they were firmly poſſeſt of it. If the Reſpect I bear to the Welfare of that Nation, and particular Friendſhip I owe to ſeveral Proprietors of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96557:11"/>Stock, had not more Influence on me than my Pique at ſuch Directors of the Company, as were the Occaſion of the Miſmanagement, I ſhould have held my Pen, and wrote nothing on this Part of the Subjest; but by reaſon I know what Pains have been taken to lead and retain a great Number of People in this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, I was reſolv'd to detect it. 'Tis true, I did not inſiſt much on it, thinking it unneceſſary on the Account of their Colonies quitting the Place; but ſince what has been offer'd already on that Head has not any Influence, I ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſome few Things more to their Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by way of Anſwer to the Original Author's Challenge to prove the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Title to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rien,</hi> either by Inheritance, Marriage, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Purchaſe, Reverſion, Surrender, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion or Conquect. I ſhall offer nothing dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, nor pretend to know all the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to it, ſo that what I offer on this Head, is, <hi>Salvo jure cujuslibit Hiſpani,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon who will take this Task upon him. If the Gentlemen of the Company will not liſten to Reaſon, let them go on and proſper; they may perhaps find it true, after they have thrown ſome more good Money after bad. I muſt only whiſper the just and modest Author in the Ear, that thoſe Perſons, whether of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Intereſt, who liſten, and make least Oppoſition to the <hi>Darien</hi> Project, are not the beſt Friends to the <hi>Scots Affrican</hi> Company;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96557:11"/>they perhaps ſee the Event of it, and will but ſmile to ſee the remaining Part of the Stock ſhipt off for <hi>Darien.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <p>DEfence of the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement at <hi>Darien,</hi> Page 4. he begins to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Title to the Province of <hi>Darien,</hi> and tells you; <hi>It is evident, that the</hi> Spaniards <hi>cannot pretend a Title to that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by Inheritance, Marriage, or the Donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Prince and People,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It being the eaſieſt Part of an Argument to deny, but not to prove a Negative, 'tis to be preſum'd, that what he hath to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance on this Head, is the Authority of the Colonies Journal, which came home laſt <hi>March:</hi> At the ſame time, it is to be believ'd, as a Preliminary, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany deſign'd to inveſt the ſame Place of <hi>Darien</hi> before any Perſon of the Colony either ſaw that Country, or could pen the Journal. If the Company depended on <hi>Buccaneer</hi>'s Stories (the Actions and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ſuch being equally regarded by political Bodies) their Foundation was ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and lame, and ſuch Evidences will ſcarce be admitted, in this Caſe, in the Courts of any Kingdom or State.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſufficiently known to all <hi>Europe,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> has been near 200 Years Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96557:12"/>of ſo much of the Continent of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> as paſſes commonly by the Names of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> which are Two Tracts of Land ſeveral Thouſand Miles extent, both on the South and North Seas: Thoſe Two vaſt Countries are join'd by a Neck of Land call'd the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien</hi> (which is about 60 or 70 Leagues long, and about 20 broad in the narroweſt Part from Sea to Sea) which Province, he may be ſaid as much to inherit and poſſeſs as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Portion of Land, of that Extent, in either <hi>Mexico</hi> or <hi>Peru;</hi> or rather more, by Reaſon his moſt important and ſtrongeſt Cities in <hi>America,</hi> are on this very <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> to wit, <hi>New Panama, St. Maris,</hi> with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſmaller Garriſons on the South-ſide, and <hi>Porto-bello, Chagre, Nombre de dios, Conception,</hi> &amp;c. on the North-ſide; beſides <hi>Carthagena</hi> adjoining to the Eaſt End of the <hi>Iſthmus.</hi> It can't be expected, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> can have a Fort and Garriſon on every Hill, or in every Creek of his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merican</hi> Dominions, nor that he ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the whole Race of the <hi>Indians</hi> in this Province of <hi>Darien,</hi> more than he does in his others. 'Tis evident, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are more numerous on this <hi>Iſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and the Parts adjoining, than on four Times ſo much Ground, in either <hi>Mexico</hi> or <hi>Peru,</hi> and where never hitherto diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96557:12"/>or interrupted in their Poſſeſſion of it, but by Pyrates, Buccaneers and Privateers, except in the Time of a declar'd War, when their Towns in <hi>Flanders</hi> and old <hi>Spain</hi> were equally lyable to Attacks.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Iſthmus</hi> is of that Importance to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that it will not admit of a Doubt amongſt reaſonable and unintereſſed Men, but that they ſhould take as much Pains to be Maſters of it, and retain the ſame, as either <hi>Mexico</hi> or <hi>Peru,</hi> by Reaſon it is the Thorough-fair and Road by which all their Treaſure and Riches from the South Sea are convey'd over to their Galleons and Flota's, on the North Sea, and ſo to <hi>Europe.</hi> 'Tis very odd, that this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould allow the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to cut off 40 Millions of <hi>Indians</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th to make Way for their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies, and to neglect this Neck of Land which joins them, and which is the <hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and Receptacle of the Whole, and without which moſt of their Collonies on the South Sea are not worth Six-pence to <hi>Old Spain.</hi> A Man's Reaſon will give him that it was as eaſie, and of more Importance to clear the Province of <hi>Darien</hi> of 40 Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Indians,</hi> as the other Parts of <hi>America</hi> of 40 Millions; and if they could ſweep off ſo many at firſt Entrance into that Country, it may be reaſonably allow'd that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96557:13"/>they have had time enough to clear this Province of ſuch a ſmall Number of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. The Suppoſition of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> neglecting this <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable and ridiculous, as if the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated Inhabitants of <hi>London</hi> ſhould have made themſelves Maſters of the City and Borough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and have neglected to ſubject the Bridge to their Dominion or Charter: Nay, the Simile in Proportion is of more Weight and Importance on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide, than this is on the City's, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' there was no other way of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with the other ſide of the <hi>Thames,</hi> than this of the Bridge.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident, that thoſe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cities and Forts are ſcatter'd over the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> being on the middle, and at both ends of it, and that they have an interrupted Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with one another. If the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rien Indians</hi> were not in Subjection, or if they were in War with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (as this Gentleman would make us believe) why might they not with the Half of thoſe 50000 Men (which <hi>pag.</hi> 5. he has pick'd out of <hi>Ringroſe</hi> the Buccanier's Dream) intercept the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Treaſure, and carry it to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Collony, if they were not able to beat them out of their Forts? 'Tis very well known, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are ſo very ſecure on that <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> that they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96557:13"/>tranſport their Treaſure over Land from <hi>Panama</hi> to <hi>Porto-bello</hi> by common Carriers, and when any of their Aſſes or Mules ſet up on the Road, they are ſo little appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the <hi>Indians,</hi> that they leave their Loads of Silver where they fall, till ſuch time as they or ſome others return that way again.</p>
            <p>He tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 9. that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are limited at both Ends of tho <hi>Iſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> excluſive by a blind Story of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Chepo</hi> and <hi>Congo,</hi> and aſſerts, that <hi>Nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre de dios</hi> is the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Boundary, at one end of the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> on the North-ſide, and that <hi>Panama</hi> and St. <hi>Maria</hi> are the Eaſtern and Weſtern Bounds on the South-ſide (by which he would take off between 30 and 40 Leagues from the Length of the <note n="*">The Author of the juſt and modeſt Vind. <hi>p.</hi> 48. makes the Length of his <hi>Iſthmus</hi> but 17 Leagues; for he ſays, that the <hi>Scotch</hi> Fort and Harbour lies between 8 or 9 Leagues from the River, or Gulph of <hi>Darien</hi> on one ſide, and <hi>Conception</hi> River on the other. He tells you like wiſe in the ſame Page, that Boats can paſs on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe Rivers to the South Sea, which is as true and poſſible as to go by Water up to the Top of the Momment.</note>
               <hi>Iſthmus</hi>) if he will re-examine the Map, he will flad that not only <hi>Nombre de dios,</hi> but likewiſe <hi>Porto-bello, Chagre</hi> and <hi>Conception,</hi> are much about the middle of the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> on the North-ſide, and that <hi>New Panama</hi> on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide is in the Cod of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96557:14"/>Bay, and oppoſite to <hi>Porto-bello;</hi> as likewiſe that <hi>Old Panama</hi> and St. <hi>Maria</hi> on the ſame ſide, are further to the Eaſt-ward, and right oppoſite to Fort St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> in <hi>Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Travellers ought to be gifted with a good Memory, for altho' he will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to be intitled to an Inch of Ground on his <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> yet he forgets himſelf and betrays his Cauſe, for <hi>p. 76.</hi> he owns that a Party of Ten <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> lived on <hi>Golden</hi> 
               <note n="*">By miſtake call'd the Iſle of <hi>Pines,</hi> in the Def.of the <hi>Scots</hi> Abdicar.</note>
               <hi>Iſland</hi> (which is within 5 Miles of Fort St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> and looks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Caledonian</hi> Harbour) till they were cut off by Capt. <hi>Ambroſio.</hi> He tells you, indeed, that it was done by Conſent, and Combination of the <hi>Darien</hi> Princes, who had only given them a Toleration to live there, and were their Tenants <hi>durante bene placito;</hi> but there's no more Authority for this Aſſertion, than that <hi>Ariſtotle's Dixit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ground where this Fact was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, was in the Diſtricht of Capt. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> who own'd himſelf to be a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captain, and which our Author indirectly confeſſeth, <hi>pag. 75.</hi> as likewiſe, that this Murder was committed but Two Months before the <hi>Scotch</hi> Collony ſettled there. The Collonies Journal acknowledgeth, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96557:14"/>Capt. * <hi>Andrews</hi> and Capt. <note n="**">Dignify'd by our laſt Author with the myſterious Names of <hi>Caiques,</hi> to ſmoother that of Captain, and imply as much Majeſty as in that of <hi>Zaar.</hi>
               </note> * <hi>Ambroſio</hi> were Enemies on the Score, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer would not break with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> whereas if this Story of our <hi>Caledonian</hi> Author be true, of that Murders being committed by Conſent, and Combination of the <hi>Darien</hi> Princes, it ſhould be taken for granted, that Capt. <hi>Andrews</hi> was as much an Enemy to <hi>Spain</hi> as <hi>Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio,</hi> or rather more, becauſe the Murder was committed in his Ground.</p>
            <p>But it is more liable to belief, that thoſe Ten <hi>Spaniards</hi> who were poſted on <hi>Golden Iſland</hi> (which is not above a Quarter of a Mile from the main Land) could think themſelves in no greater Danger than ſo many <hi>Engliſh</hi> in ſome Mountanous part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where a Rapparee Party could with the ſame Eaſe cut their Throats. Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor acknowledgeth, that they were poſted there for a Look-out, to give Notice of any Veſſels that appear'd on that Coaſt; and it may be the eaſier credited, that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> employ'd that Iſland or Promontory for that Uſe, by reaſon the Author of, <hi>The Juſt and Modeſt Vindicat.</hi> of the <hi>Darien</hi> Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, innocently tells you, that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> call that Iſland by the Name of <hi>Guarda,</hi> (in his 48<hi>th Page)</hi> which of it ſelf
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96557:15"/>implies the Uſe which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (not newly, but of a long Date) have made of it.</p>
            <p>After all, I muſt tell, that Capt. <hi>Andrews</hi> had no Hand in this Murder, but <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> who came with his Gang from his Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is above 40 Miles diſtant) and treacherouſly ſurpriz'd them. Neither is it to be imagin'd, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (who are very Wary and Politick) can be thought to be guilty of ſuch Weakneſs, as to expoſe ſo ſmall a Party amongſt <hi>Indians,</hi> their Native Enemies, but rather that they thought that Party ſecure enough in a Country which was under their Obedience.</p>
            <p>So much I have offer'd to demonſtrate the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inheritance: As for their Title by Marriage, 'tis evident enough, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> has more Subjects born of <hi>Indian</hi> (beſides Mooriſh) Mothers in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> than he has of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> in <hi>Europe:</hi> Nay, if it were not for the Liberty which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to marry with the <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Moors,</hi> it were impoſſible they could plant and inhabit that vaſt Continent; and 'tis well enough known, that this Progeny of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is of moſt uſe in defending thoſe Countries, and retaining them under the Obedience and Subjection of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Donation of Prince or People, I don't pretend to know the <hi>Spaniſh Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Archives and Regiſters, more than our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96557:15"/>Author can prove the Contrary. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have more to ſhow for their Inveſtiture, than the <hi>Caledonian</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil has brought home with them. Only this I can be poſitive in, that theſe <hi>Dariens</hi> acknowledge, that they have had no Head or Emperor of their own Nation, for above theſe 150 Years, which may be reckon'd to be about the Date of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Settling there; and if I am not miſtaken, the Colonies Journal (altho' cautiouſly enough calculated) acknowledgeth the ſame.</p>
            <p>As for Conqueſt (he ſays in the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, Page 4.) <hi>'Tis ridiculous to alledge it, ſince the</hi> Dariens <hi>are in actual Poſſeſſion of their Liberty, and were never ſubdu'd, nor receiv'd any</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Garriſon or Governour amongſt them.</hi> The laſt Author who para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſeth on him, aſſerts likewiſe that thoſe Captains are all ſovereign and independent Princes, but coming cloſſer to the Text, tells us, from <hi>Purffendorf</hi> and the Civilians, Page 73. (making the Suppoſition of their being conquer'd:) That <hi>per ſolam Viminju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam, non poſſe alicui Jus quaeri,</hi> &amp;c. and from Grotius; That <hi>Actus imperii invaſoris quos excercet nullam Vim habere poſſant ex ipſius Jure, quod nullum eſt.</hi> By both theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, this modeſt Author may as Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally claim a Right to all the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Towns
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96557:16"/>and Dominions, as to his <hi>Peninſula,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Fort St. <hi>Andrew</hi> ſtands, if he can but ſet his Foot there, and perſwade the <hi>Indians</hi> to revolt; ſince he ſo plainly ſays, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made an unjuſt Invaſion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over the <hi>American</hi> Princes and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, which no ways obliges them to pay Fealty, or continue in their Obedience long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than they find it in their Power to free themſelves from the Yoke. He fouls Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per enough in Preaching up this Doctrine, altho' it had been Time enough Seven Years hence, when the <hi>Caledonians</hi> had ſurer Footing on the <hi>Iſthmus:</hi> But altho' thoſe Civilians allow him ſuch Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, yet he will find ſome prevailing Arguments in the Treaties between the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> to curb him, which out-balances his Civilian Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities. So that we muſt agree to ſuffer the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to be Conqueror and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of thoſe Parts of <hi>America,</hi> eſpecially where he has Cities, Forts, Garriſons and Mines.</p>
            <p>But to return to the original Author, who ſays, that it is ridiculous to alledge any ſuch Title to <hi>Darien,</hi> where the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives are in actual Poſſeſſion of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. He is either Brazen-fac'd, elſe he has forgot that St. <hi>Maria, Tubaconti,</hi> Old and New <hi>Panama, Nombre de dios, Porto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96557:16"/>Conception,</hi> &amp;c. are ſcatter'd over that very <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> if I ſhould ſay nothing of <hi>Guarda</hi> or <hi>Golden Iſland</hi> it ſelf, where thoſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> reſided. 'Tis well enough known, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have Mines in ſeveral Parts of that <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> and ſome not above 12 Leagues from the Collony, without any Guard, ſave the Overſeers and other Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Aſſiſtants to keep the <hi>Negro</hi>'s to Work.</p>
            <p>I can't underſtand how thoſe <hi>Dariens</hi> can be ſaid to enjoy their Liberty, where there are ſo many Cities, Forts and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons to curb them. 'Tis very unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that his Warlike Prince, called <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſio,</hi> ſhould live ſo occultly, as not to have a Path to his Royal Pallace, but that from the Capital Port of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom a Man muſt wade Eleven Times through the ſame River, up to the Middle, and bruſh through Thickets, whoſe Twigs have not been cut nor prun'd ſince the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, before he can come to his Wigwam City, altho' it is not above an Hour's Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, if the Road were beat and even. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſio</hi> and <hi>Diego</hi> have indeed piſs'd in the Pumpdale, and both live obſcurely with, may be, 30 or 40 in their ſeveral Gangs, whom a Dozen of Men with Fire Arms would ſoon reduce, if it were poſſible to ferret them out.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:96557:17"/>
            <p>As for <hi>Wafer</hi> and <hi>Dampier</hi> whom our Author adduces, <hi>Page</hi> 4. for his Evidences, neither of theſe pretend to know <hi>Diego</hi> or <hi>Ambroſio, Dampter</hi> having only croſs'd the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> and <hi>Wafer</hi> ſtaid not above Three Months there, with his <hi>Lacenta,</hi> with whom after he had ſojourn'd till his Leg was well, croſs'd the Country, and took Water at <hi>La-Sounds</hi> Key, which lies amongſt the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balla</hi>'s, and about 20 Leagues to the North-Weſt of the <hi>Caledonian</hi> Collony: And if <hi>Wafer</hi> ſays, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the <hi>Indians</hi> on the North-ſide of the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> a little beyond <hi>Porto-bello,</hi> I have no occaſion to diſprove him, ſince he does not deny, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand on the South-ſide, and likewiſe on this ſide of <hi>Porto-bello,</hi> where <hi>New Caledonia</hi> lies. See <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Of the Def. of the</hi> Scots <hi>Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Our Author either ſums up his Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence wrong, elſe he truſts to the ſlight En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of his Readers.</p>
            <p>In the Two next Paragraphs he cites the ſame Evidences, and tells you a Tale of a Cock and a Bull, how <hi>Batt. Sharp</hi> in the Year, 1680, landed at <hi>Golden Iſland,</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd one of thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> Captains, <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> and his Eldeſt Son, <hi>King Golden Cape,</hi> and having join'd thoſe <hi>Darien</hi> Princes (of their own Creation) took St. <hi>Maria,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted <hi>Panama,</hi> and made Prize of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96557:17"/>
               <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships on the South Sea, and how afterwards when he came to be try'd for thoſe Pyracies in <hi>England,</hi> the <note n="*">The Author of, <hi>The juſt and modest Vindicat.</hi> as good as gives <hi>Wafer</hi> the Lye here; for <hi>p.</hi> 90. he ſays, the <hi>Darien</hi> Captains always rul'd within themſelves, and never had any other <hi>Indian</hi> Sovereign.</note> Emperor of <hi>Darien</hi>'s Commiſſion clear'd him.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident by the Conceſſion of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> themſelves, and by the Collonies Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that there has been no <hi>Indian</hi> Monarch or Emperor in that Country for an Age or two by paſt; in the next place, if <hi>Batt</hi>'s Jury had any great Inclination to hang him, they might have enquir'd further into the Emperor, or his Secretary who wrote the Commiſſion: I dare ſay, that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pen both worded and ſign'd it; for in my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels in that Country, I could meet with neither Prince nor Clergyman that knew a Letter of the Book. I want to know who Commanded as <hi>Generalliſſimo</hi> at the Taking of St. <hi>Maria,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Prizes at Sea, and when thoſe Princes ſerv'd on board, who was Captain, and who Cook? It ſeems the <hi>Darien</hi> Empire was very low at the Landing of Capt. <hi>Sharp,</hi> when he and his 330 Men could give ſuch Life, and do ſuch Feats againſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> on that <hi>Iſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> when <hi>Baſil Ringroſe,</hi> one of the ſame Crew, his <hi>Darien</hi> King could do ſo little
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96557:18"/>with his 50000 Men, to revenge the Rape of his Royal Daughter. 'Tis pity the Jury did not oblige Mr. <hi>Sharp</hi> to produce his Diſcharge, or Certificate from that Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: <hi>But let the Pitcher go ne'er ſo oft to the Well, it will be ſure to come home crack'd ſome time or other;</hi> ſo this poor Sojour or Sailor of Fortune has not the ſame Luck every where, for none of thoſe Commiſſions would ſerve his turn about 16 Months ago at the Iſland of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> where he was doom'd to die in a Halter for one of the like Enterprizes, and had nothing elſe to truſt to than the K. of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Mercy.</p>
            <p>Our Author to confirm all, ſays in the ſame Paragraph, <hi>Page</hi> 5. This is the more remarkable, becauſe thoſe very Princes or their Succeſſors are now in League with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and have joyfully receiv'd them into their Country. I anſwer to this, I refer my ſelf to the 58 and 59 <hi>Pag. Of the Def. of the Scots Abd.</hi> where Captain <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreas</hi> (whom both of us agree on, to be the ſuppoſed Emperors Succeſſor) tells the tragical Story of their joining thoſe Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caneers and Privateers, and how they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for the ſame, after theſe had got the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Plunder (which was their Errand) and left them expos'd to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fury.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Ambroſio</hi> and <hi>Diego's</hi> Willingneſs to receive the <hi>Scotch</hi> Colony amongſt them,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96557:18"/>it may be reaſonably believ'd, becauſe thoſe are outlaws and never expect to be pardon'd, the Former for the Murder of thoſe <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> on <hi>Golden Iſland,</hi> and the other for At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking Three Prieſts in their Cell or Chappel, and Murdering of them, and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Alter of it's Furniture; whereof, <hi>Diego</hi>'s Son brought the Sacerdotal Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Challice to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Colony, and ſold the ſame to Captain <hi>Frazer,</hi> for little or nothing. Thoſe Outlaws will not only be glad of the <hi>Scots,</hi> 
               <note n="*">Witneſs <hi>Diego</hi>'s admitting Cap. <hi>Long</hi> in the <hi>Rupert</hi> Prize to ſettle in his Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the Gulph of <hi>Darien,</hi> about the ſame time the <hi>Scots</hi> ſettled.</note> but of the <hi>Dutch, French, Danes,</hi> nay <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> if they thought any of theſe, or all of them could protect and ſhelter them from Juſtice. Nay, they are ſo little able to make any Oppoſition, that I could engage to be one of 20 Men to go over that <hi>Iſthmus</hi> over their Bellies, providing the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would wink at it.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph, <hi>Pag. 6. Then as to any Claim, by Virtue of Poſſeſſion the</hi> Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards <hi>have not the leaſt Ground of a Plea, all they can alledge on this Head is, that they were once admitted by the Conſent of Capt.</hi> Diego, <hi>another of the</hi> Darien <hi>Princes, to work on ſome Gold Mines within</hi> 15 <hi>Leagues of the</hi> Scotch <hi>Settlement; but 'tis plain, that this makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96557:19"/>for their Purpoſe, that Prince admitting them not as Proprietors, but as Labourers, and when they broke the Conditions on which they were admitted,</hi> VIZ. <hi>To allow the</hi> Dariens <hi>ſuch and ſuch Shares of the Product they were expell'd again by Force,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our Author having compos'd a handſom Story of <hi>Diego</hi> (whoſe Kingdom is the 3d from the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony) ſhuffles in Mr. <hi>Wafer</hi> for Evidence, whereas he owns himſelf, that he never ſaw ſuch a Man as Capt. <hi>Diego;</hi> and as for his <hi>Lacenta,</hi> that Prince is ſuch a Stranger to the <hi>Indians</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, that altho' ſome Pains was taken to enquire after him, yet he could not be heard of; but there being 17 or 18 Years between <hi>Wafer</hi>'s and the <hi>Scots</hi> ſojourning in that Country, <hi>Lacenta</hi> in the time might probably be choak'd with ſome of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hemp amongſt the other Princes, whom the Privatiers and Buccaniers deſerted, and left to care of themſelves.</p>
            <p>This mighty Story of <hi>Diego</hi> is ſo ill coyn'd, that it would make a Man ſick to trace it. He owns thoſe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mines to be within 15 Leagues of the Collony (1 ſay 12) and <hi>Diego</hi> is the Third Captain, or <hi>Zaar,</hi> from the Collony towards St. <hi>Maria</hi> (as appears, <hi>p.</hi> 79 and 80) <hi>Andreas</hi> the Companies Landlord being the Firſt, <hi>Pouſſigo</hi> the Clergy-man (as our Author dignifies him) the Second; whereby it may be eaſily conceiv'd what a powerful and large Government <hi>Diego</hi> can have to hire the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as Labourers; and after theſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> had ſpent ſome Years in opening thoſe Mines, and bringing them to Perfection, they ſhould be expell'd when King <hi>Diego</hi> took Snuff. This Strength of <hi>Diego</hi> is ſo very incoherent with the late Action which happen'd in <hi>January</hi> laſt, when 26 <hi>Spaniards</hi> being order'd from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96557:19"/>St. <hi>Maria</hi> to march over the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> in order to view the <hi>Scots,</hi> came through <hi>Diego</hi>'s Ground, where, if the <hi>Indians</hi> had been their open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo ſmall a Party would ſcarce have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd; yet <hi>Diego</hi>'s Men were ſo unable to oppoſe them, that they took upon them to pilot them to a convenient Place, where they might view the <hi>Scots,</hi> and in the mean time ſome of <hi>Diego</hi>'s Men came to the Government of <hi>Pedro</hi> (the Defunct <hi>Andreas</hi> his Succeſſor) and ſo to the Collony with the News; on which Mr. <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomry,</hi> with a Detachment of a 100 Men, were piloted by them to the Spot where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> lay.</p>
            <p>In this very Action Four Things are remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 1. The Weakneſs of <hi>Diego</hi>'s and <hi>Pedro</hi>'s Forces, who were not able to cut off the Heads of ſuch a Handful, but that they muſt come to the Collony for Aſſiſtance. 2. The Confidence which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> put in the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Diego</hi> and <hi>Pedro.</hi> 3. The <hi>Scotch</hi> Party leaving their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and going with the <hi>Indians,</hi> with a Deſign to attack thoſe 26 <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who were lying ſome Leagues off on the Bank of a ſmall River, and who finding themſelves betray'd by thoſe <hi>Indians,</hi> fir'd upon them, and ſo retreated to their next Garriſon of <hi>Tubaconti.</hi> 4. That this being the only Fight between the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> the Breach of Peace was founded on it, and Letters of Mark and Repriſal granted by the Collony to <hi>Pilkinton</hi> and <hi>Sands,</hi> Maſters of <hi>Jamaica</hi> Sloops.</p>
            <p>The Story of <hi>Diego</hi>'s beating the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from the Gold Mines tells very ackwardly (our Author imputing this Rupture to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> beating and male-treating <hi>Diego</hi>'s People, when
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96557:20"/>they came to ask their Shares) but to wave the Improbability of this Story, and admit it for a Truth; 'tis to be preſum'd, that when <hi>Diego</hi> fell upon thoſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> and ſlew them, he did not allow them time to blow up thoſe Mines, or fill them up with Rubbiſh, that they might not be ſerviceable to him or his Friends afterwards; and it might have been reaſonably expected, that <hi>Diego</hi> ſhould either have made a Preſent of thoſe Mines to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Collony (for Houſe-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) or at leaſt have ſuffer'd them to dig up ſome of the Gold to buy Proviſions, and keep them from ſtarving, that thereby they might have been the more enabled to aſſiſt them againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and reſtore them to their Ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, beſides, leading them a nearer Way to the Kingdom of Heaven, than that which the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> cut out for them.</p>
            <p>The Gentlement of the Collony were very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt (as he tells you in the 78 and 79 <hi>pag.</hi>) <hi>When they were inform'd by ſome</hi> French <note n="*">A pretty ſafe Name for two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>French</hi> Pyrates, and a <hi>Molletoo,</hi> all Natives of <hi>Martine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> who were oblig'd to live among the <hi>Indians,</hi> by reaſon they were ſtable to be hang'd on any Chriſtian Ground, whereon they could be caught.</note>
               <hi>Refugees, that with a</hi> 100 <hi>Men they could be Maſters of ſome Gold and Silver Mines belonging to the</hi> Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, <hi>but they were ſo gifted with the Grace of Self-denyal, that they would not liſten to it, till once the</hi> Spaniard <hi>offer'd ſome Hoſtility.</hi> We now find that this, which our Author would have to be the Hoſtile Act, was committed in <hi>January;</hi> but it is to be admir'd that the Collony ſhould only ſend Sloops out to pilfer a few Fiſher-mens Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou's, and Houſes at <hi>Teleu,</hi> near <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and not have ſpar'd the foreſaid 100 Men to reduce the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mines to their Subjection; or if they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96557:20"/>were afraid to offend the <hi>Span.</hi> by Land, they had not ſent a few of their num. to their Frd. and Ally <hi>Diego</hi>'s Gold Mines, where there was no Danger to be apprehended of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> looking that Prince in the Face; and not have laid in Fort St. <hi>Andrew</hi> making Childrens Shooes after the War was thus begun from <hi>January</hi> to <hi>June,</hi> and at laſt be forc'd to quit the glorious Project for want of Proviſions, when at the ſame time they were tantaliz'd with Veſſels loaded with good Food on one ſide of them, and Mines full of Gold on the other for want of Grace to attack them. I wiſh our Author would reviſe thoſe Paragraphs in the <hi>5th</hi> and <hi>6th Pages,</hi> as alſo in the 78 and <hi>79th,</hi> and ſee if the Stories are of a piece, or if they will hold water.</p>
            <p>I am rather inclin'd to believe that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> is more Maſter than Servant amongſt the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> and likewiſe, that he does not eaſily part with any Place he once gets into his Poſſeſſion, eſpecially Gold Mines: 'Tis very rare to hear of the <hi>Spaniard</hi>'s being beaten off by the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and it's more improbable on this ſmall Tract of Ground, call'd the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> where his Cities, Forts, Garriſons and Mines are ſo cloſely planted, and where if he wanted any Aſſiſtance, he can ſooner have Supplies brought thither, than to any other Part of <hi>New Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Buccaniers and Privatiers were at the ſtrongeſt (muſtering about 1300) and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd St. <hi>Maria,</hi> and ſome other Places on the South Sea, neither they nor the <hi>Indians</hi> durſt venture too keep them above a Week or Ten Days, being jealous of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> rallying with new Umbro's, and attacking them again; but having robb'd and deſtroy'd what they could,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96557:21"/>ſculk'd away to ſome new Place (may be 1 or 200 Leagues diſtant) and always left the <hi>Indians</hi> of of the laſt Place, if any join'd them, to capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late for themſelves. If they fought under thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> Princes to recover their Country for them, it might reaſonably be expected, that they ſhould left them poſſeſt of ſuch Places as they recover'd out of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Hands, but there's nothing like this in all the Buccaniers Chronicl.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, if you'l take my Word, I'll tell you, that this Story of <hi>Diego</hi>'s beating the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from their Mines is ſo far a Miſtake, that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> were at work on them when the <hi>Scots</hi> landed there, having only an Intendant, with 50 <hi>Spaniards</hi> to overſee 500 <hi>Negro</hi>'s, who wrought them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they deſert thoſe Mines notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Neighbourhood of the <hi>Scots,</hi> tho' per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they might reinforce their Guards. And notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Montgomrie</hi> was ſo near them with that ſelect Party of 100 Men, and and thoſe Three <hi>Indian</hi> Princes to ſtand by him, yet he did not think it expedient to diſturb them, but ſtisfy'd himſelf with <hi>Redpith</hi>'s famous Captain, <hi>Dan Domingo de la rada.</hi> As for the Teſtimony which our Author would draw <hi>Wafer</hi> in for here; he neither knows any thing of <hi>Diego,</hi> nor of thoſe Prieſts, theſe being murder'd many Years after his leaving that Country.</p>
            <p>Our Author proceeds thus to the <hi>7th Page,</hi> where he tells us, that the aforeſaid pretended Titles being fully confuted, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> can lay no Claim to <hi>Darien,</hi> but what they plead from the Pope's general Grant of <hi>America,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>How ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous it is to urge the Pope's Grant amongſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and how precarious it is amongst Papiſts themſelves, but admitting it to be enough to juſtifie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96557:21"/>their Title, it is eaſie to prove that the</hi> Spaniards <hi>have forfeited all the Right they can claim by Virtue of that Grant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Buccanier Evidences are laid aſide for ſome time, there being no room for them here, wherefore he tells us ſuch another Tale in a Tub of the Biſhop of <hi>Chiapa,</hi> who it ſeems, was Teſty with his Sovereign Lord the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> becauſe that Prince did not anſwer the End of the Pope's Grant, but minded more the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure than Souls of the <hi>Americans,</hi> and rail'd at him for not Reſtoring to the Executors of thoſe dead <hi>Indians,</hi> whatever he or his Inſtruments had taken from them, and pleads Queen <hi>Iſſobella</hi>'s Requeſt for the ſame, when ſhe was on her Death-bed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I mayn't waſte too much Paper in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering thoſe Three or Four Paragraphs, take this in ſhort, that the Biſhop of <hi>Chiapa</hi> had not the ſame Senſe of Money in his Age, as the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners or <hi>Propoganda fide</hi> Gentlemen have in ours, elſe he had made leſs Noiſe. If the General Aſſembly ſhould fraught their Diſciples with never ſo ſtrict Inſtructions, to eſtabliſh the Kirk Diſcipline, yet if <hi>Praedicant Paterſon</hi> ſhould form an Anabaptiſt Government there, the Company would ſcarce think their Title to that Country thereby forfeited. Our Author ſomewhere elſe in his Politicks thinks it expedient for the ſpeedier deſtroying of Antichriſt, to ſeize on his Pouch or Purſe: It was reaſonable the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſhould make uſe of the ſame Maxim, and imitate <hi>Moſes</hi> after his deſcending from the Mount, in taking away the Golden Calf from his Brethren, and ſuch Inſtruments of Idolatry.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> has been guilty of all our Author lays to his Charge, and hath not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerd the End of the Pope's Donation, pray
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96557:22"/>whether is the Pope or the <hi>Scotch</hi> Company judge of it? If the Pope thinks fit to revoke the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Charter, 'tis time enough then for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to take the Charge of the <hi>American</hi> Souls upon them; but as he has done nothing like this as yet, but on the contrary has granted a large Subſidy on the <hi>American</hi> Church to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it, the Company may appear officious in meddling with his Holineſs's Buſineſs, and give the World too much reaſon to believe that their Deſign is not only to expel the <hi>Spaniard</hi> out of <hi>Darien,</hi> but likewiſe out of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> under this Religious Pretext. I want to know whether <hi>Paterſon's</hi> and the Companies Project was to take the Cure of the <hi>American</hi> Souls, or Treaſure upon them? If the former, then 1048 Levites and two Soldiers, had been fitter Miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to <hi>Darien,</hi> than two Preachers and 1048 ſuch Lay Elders; and inſtead of 2 or 3000 Buchaniers Pieces, Piſtols, Daggers, and Drums proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; they ought to have follow'd the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions annex'd to the Original Commiſſion of, <hi>ite &amp; pradicate,</hi> and gone without <hi>Staff</hi> or <hi>Scrip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Altho our <hi>Author</hi> by the ſtrain of his Pen, ſhews that he has been a conſiderable time from Home, yet he betrays ſomething now and then, to confirm us, that good ſtore of the Kirk Milk lurks ſtill in the receſſes of his Noſe; for he is not ſatisfy'd with beating the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of <note n="*">The juſt and modeſt Author of the <hi>Vindicat.</hi> pag. 84, and 85, admits the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Title to be valid to his <hi>American</hi> Poſſeſſious. But in other Places where he is Angry, he curs them off again with a ſtrook of the ſabe Pen.</note>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi> with his Religious Cant, but muſt ſtick to the good Old Way of Murdering his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Reputation, that by once rendring him Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he may muſter the whole Kennel of Curs to bark him out of Town. In the 7th, 8th, and 9th Pages, he Whines in the ſame Strain as the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96557:22"/>Hypocrites in the Goſpel did, when they had a devouring Deſign on Widows Houſes.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Subject in Debate, ſince our <hi>Author</hi> after all his Railing, is ſuch a Hero as to admit the Pope's Donation to be ſo valid as to give the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſome Claim to <hi>America,</hi> I'll be quits with him in Civility, and paſs from the Pope's Donation altogether, and ſtick to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Poſſeſſion; which they have had not only of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru</hi> in Geneal, but of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Darian</hi> in Particular, by Preſcription of a great many Years; where their ſeveral Towns, Forts, Gariſons and Mines, are ſufficient Evidences of it; and beſides theſe Legal Infeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, can bring 50 of thoſe <hi>Darien</hi> Indians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Banner, to one that will appear againſt them, to juſtifie their Right of Dominion. All this being duly conſider'd, I can't ſee where the Audacious Affront lyes that's offer'd to His <hi>Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Majeſty, by the <hi>Catholick</hi> King, who only aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts his Right, and ſays, That ſome <hi>Scots</hi> in the time of Peace, without any Injury Offer'd, have Invaded the Heart of his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions: 'Tis very unaccountable, that this Cholerick Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould take his <hi>Catholick</hi> Majeſty by the Noſe, for ſaying, That the Church ſtands in the Church-yard.</p>
            <p>So much then for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Title to <hi>Darien,</hi> by Inheritance, Marriage, Donation, Poſſeſſion and Conqueſt; as for the Purchaſe and Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I was not Witneſs to thoſe Tranſactions; but Reaſon will allow theſe to follow in Courſe, if the others be good. As for Reverſion, I can't well comprehend our <hi>Author</hi>'s Meaning; for it cannot be ſaid, That the <hi>Spaniard</hi> has either Quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or Mortgag'd that Province to the <hi>Indians,</hi> ſince he remains ſtill on the Spot, and in Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, and in all appearance is like to do after we are Dead.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:96557:23"/>
            <p>If what I have offer'd in Anſwer to this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Challenge, will ſerve to demonſtrate the <hi>Spaniard</hi>'s Right to that <hi>Iſthmus;</hi> there will be no more occaſion for <hi>Puffendorf</hi> nor <hi>Hugo Grotius;</hi> ſo that the only Standard we are left to walk by, is the Treaties of Peace between <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which both theſe Authors, the Defender and Vindicator of the <hi>Darien</hi> Settlement, can neither wreſt nor ſqueeze any thing from to ſerve their Turn: After they have ſaid all they can think of on that Head, they tell you, <q>
                  <note n="*">Def. of the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</note> That all that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from thoſe <hi>Treaties,</hi> is, that they are a Mutual Security for the peaceable Poſſeſſion of what each Crown Poſſeſt, and no more.</q> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> deſire no more benefit of theſe Treaties, than what thoſe Authors herein allow them. 'Tis evident e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, That by thoſe <hi>Treaties,</hi> His Majeſty got conſiderably from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to wit, Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Title to the Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> which was taken from the <hi>Spaniard</hi> during the <hi>Exile</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> II. but likewiſe a full Right to all the Colonies in <hi>America,</hi> his Subjects were then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of. And if thoſe <hi>Treaties</hi> were no Fence to the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> I don't know what ſhould oblige him to make ſuch large Gifts, and renounce his Title to Place wwhich ſome time or other he might be in a condition to Recover. If the Subjects of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> may when they pleaſe, Seat themſelves on <hi>Darien,</hi> or elſewhere on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Coaſt, then the <hi>Spaniard</hi> has no Benefit by thoſe <hi>Treaties:</hi> But I am rather apt to believe, (as our Author has hit it) <hi>That they were made for a Mutual Security of what oach Crown poſſeſt,</hi> and no more.</p>
            <p>What our <hi>Authors</hi> would ſqueeze from thoſe <hi>Treaties,</hi> is, <hi>That neither Party is excluded from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96557:23"/>his Dominions in</hi> America <hi>upon Waſtes, <note place="margin">Def. of the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement <hi>pag. 11.</hi>
                  </note> or by conſent of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in fuch Places, as have never yet been poſſeſt by</hi> Spain, <hi>or</hi> Great Britain. Altho there's nothing expreſt ſo in thoſe <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and if I ſhould yield them this Gloſs they ſet on them, yet I can't ſee how the <hi>Caledonian</hi> Settlement can take any place here, becauſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion can't properly be enlarg'd before there be a Footing; and when thoſe <hi>Treaties</hi> were conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there was no word of a <hi>Caledonian</hi> Colony.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Caribdee</hi> Iſlands cannot well be enlarg'd, but if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>French</hi> have not Room e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough on them, they may remove to ſuch Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Ones as are not the Property of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Prince in Alliance with their Sovereigns. As for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Colonies on the main Land, they may enlarge their Dominions far enough round them, if they will, and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> never quarrel with them, ſo long as they don't come within the Tropicks, and meddle with his <hi>Noli me tangere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Dr. <hi>Cox</hi> and the <hi>Creolians,</hi> who ſettl'd and remov'd in the Bay of <hi>Campechy,</hi> they were in the Right, in Forming, ſuch Flying-Camps, for when any of them were caught by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> they pay'd for it, and had their Mends in their own Hands: And the Author of the <hi>juſt and modeſt Vindic.</hi> p. 168, is as good as ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd as to that Part of it, altho' he does not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Judgment of his Majeſty, the Lords Juſtices, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Council, who being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd by ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Marchants for a Patent to ſettle on the ſame <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> ſome Time before the <hi>Scotch</hi> Company had got the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, refus'd it on the Score of its being contrary to the Treaties of Peace. He would inſinuate, that the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> refus'd it for other Reaſons:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96557:24"/>But if our Author will look back and enquire a little further, he will find, that Sr. <hi>Tho. Mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diford,</hi> Governor of <hi>Jamaica</hi> propos'd the ſame in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d. and it being can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſs'd at Court, and the Legality of it exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it was refus'd on no other State-Reaſons than its being contrary to the Treaties between their Britannick and Catholick Majeſties; but our Author being dexterous, never wants a Hole to creep out at, by Inſinuating, that his Majeſty's and the Lords Juſtices refuſing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects that Patent, was not on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its Injuſtice, but upon Motives of State, which is as much to ſay, that it was not Time to diſoblige his Catholick Majeſty.</p>
            <p>As for their Inſtances of the independent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignties in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> which are inclos'd with other Princes Dominions, the Caſes are no ways parallel, ſo long as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are Maſters of all the fortify'd Places and Towns on the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> and the <hi>Indians</hi> ſcarce of a Wigwam they can call their own. <hi>And as for the King of</hi> 
               <note n="*">Def. of the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement, <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </note> Darien'<hi>s inviting the Buccaniers to aſſiſt him to retake his Country.</hi> Altho' the King were not Fictitious yet by this innocent Story our Author concedes, that he had loſt his Country to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when he wanted Aſſiſtance to recover it out of their Hands: At this Rate the <hi>Scotch</hi> Company may not only elbow the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of <hi>Darien,</hi> but likewiſe out of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> ſince in the ſame <hi>Page</hi> he means as much by declaring the <hi>Indians</hi> the natural Lords of <hi>Darien,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> only Tyrannical Uſurpers. But to dive a little further into the Probability of this Story, I want to know where that People, call'd Buccaniers liv'd, whom the King of <hi>Darien</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to his Aſſiſtance, or when they joyn'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96557:24"/>him and recover'd ſome of thoſe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Towns, they did not leave him in Poſſeſſion of them? 'Tis more reaſonable to believe, that that Kind of Vermin which feeds on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Spoil, went to the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> on the Account of its Communication with the South Sea, and the Paſſage by which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Riches are tranſported to the Galleons on the North Side, and perſwaded thoſe poor <hi>Indians</hi> to revolt, and pilot them to ſuch Places where they thought to get Booty, which is the more probable, by reaſon theſe <hi>Indians</hi> paid dear for it always when the Buccaniers deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
            <p>As for Capt. <hi>Saukins</hi> his ſending a Letter to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Panama,</hi> wherein he juſtify'd his Proceedings, and aſſerted this imaginary King of <hi>Darien</hi> to be natural Lord of <hi>Panama;</hi> I know that old Buccaneer ſo very well, that I believe it to be true, if <hi>Saukins</hi> had carry'd the Meſſage himſelf, he might perhaps have got a ſuitable Anſwer.</p>
            <p>As in the <hi>Def. of</hi> Scots <hi>Abdicat.</hi> I declin'd Anſwering the fiery Ejaculations of the firſt Author, either by offering any Thing againſt the Legality of the <hi>Octroy</hi> it ſelf, or the Intereſt of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation in applying themſelves to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Trade, believing the former to be great and well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, for the Advantage and Proſperity of the Country in general, and that the latter is ſo juſt, that I yield both the Theme and Doctrine of the juſt and modeſt Vindicator to be good ſo far as it relates thereto; ſo I ſtill ſhun med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with any Paſſages, either in the Firſt or Second Author that relates to the ſeparate Intereſt of the Two Nations, but ftick cloſe to the <hi>Darien</hi> Title which is the main Subject in Debate, and as the Original Author cites. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. from Dr. <hi>Saffold—Sublata cauſa tollitur Effectus,</hi> if the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Title to that <hi>Iſihmus</hi> be found to be good; <hi>Then the Cauſe of the Complaint ceaſes; and the Company ought to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to that which will turn to Account, and not run on Meaſures to imbroil not only the Iſle of</hi> Great Britain, <hi>but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps all</hi> Europe <hi>in a new War.</hi> If the thinking Part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind will but reflect on the Steps that have been made to <hi>Darien,</hi> to wit, in ſending their Ships and Men to ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign a Country which was ſo lyable to be diſputed, and that with Six Months Proviſions, 2. The Companies Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect in Supplying them with more. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Diſperſing ſuch Declarations clandeſtinly over the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Iſlands and Plantations (which of Neceſlity muſt meet with Oppoſition) to invite People thence to ſettle on <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rien;</hi> they will find that there have been ſome private Wheels in this Machin that have brought it to the State wherein it now is, to ſay no more on't.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:96557:25"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF I have treated the laſt <hi>Caledonias</hi> Author with more Civility than he merits, 'tis becauſe theſe Sheets were finiſh'd and in the Preſs before I was ſire that <hi>Fergaſon</hi> was the <hi>juſt and modeſt Man,</hi> till now his Looks ſticking in the ſeveral Bookſellers Hands obliges him to diſperſe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Gratis,</hi> as the other Quack-bills, and ſo gives me the Opportunity of being fully confirm'd in the Matter. His Employment and Morals are ſo notorions already, that any thing I ſhould ſay of him would add but little to his Infamy, and would be ſo much loft on him. Wherefore, in reply to thoſe Scurrilities he falſly aſperſes me with, I ſhall only put him in mind, that his Pot had not boil'd ſo well, if he had not been better paid for his Shuffling, Plotting and Tricking, than I have for what I have juſtly offer'd in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of His Majeſty's Proceedings, and to unblind a great Number of well-meaning Perſons, who are induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly led into this Miſtake, by ſome particular Gentlemen behind the Curtain, who poſſeſs them with a Notion, that the Miſmanagement and Miſcarriage of their Affairs was not occaſion'd by the Directors of that Company, but by the Government of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: And how far this will appear to be true, when it comes to be either calmly or warmly canvas'd, Time will diſcover: The greateſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that I have of any Reward at preſent is the Daggers and Piſtols, wherewith I am daily threaten'd, and nightly way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid; againſt which Dr. <hi>Ferguſon</hi> in all his Machinations was always ſure to fence himſelf. Trade being very dead of late, he is reſolv'd to play at ſmall Game rather than ſtand out; but altho' the conceited Polltician ſhades himſelf under the Skreen of <hi>Patria ſua,</hi> to calumniate the Government of that <hi>Hoſpitium,</hi> whoſe Bread he hath ſo long eat, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hath been ſo pamper'd; it is neither out of Friendſhip to the Company, Nation, or Kirk, (the laſt of which he plainly enough demonſtrates, <hi>p.</hi> 205, &amp; 206.) but to blow the Coal of Sedition, ſet <hi>Great Britain</hi> in a Flame, and bring his own Marks to bear; which may be the eaſier conceiv'd by minding of what Sect and Kindney thoſe Gentlemen are, who eſpouſe the <hi>Darien</hi> Intereſt with the moſt Heat. To flab the <hi>Knave</hi> in <hi>Newgate,</hi> were but to incourage the old Sinner in his Trade, and put him in a Way to get Money; whereas giving him his <hi>Mittimus,</hi> and ſending hith home to his own Country, to drive the Trade there, and giving him leave freely to make what he can of this Text, would be the moſt mortifying and ſuitable Puniſhment that could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
